Finding Aid for Peace Corps Office (University of Michigan) records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Peace Corps Office (University of Michigan) records 2010-2015
University of Michigan. Peace Corps Office.
2.18 GB and archived website
2014125 Aa 3
Office responsible for administering Peace Corps programming at the University of Michigan. Collection consists of video and web content surrounding the fiftieth anniversary celebration in 2010 of the proposal of the Peace Corps at the Michigan Union by Sen. John F. Kennedy.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by University of Michigan Peace Corps Office (donor no. 11160 ), in August, 2014.
The collection is open to research.
The University of Michigan Peace Corps office helps students pursue service opportunities with the Peace Corps and disseminates information about the organization to the campus community. The history of Peace Corps activities at the University of Michigan dates back to the conception and creation of the Peace Corps itself. In September 1960, Senator and then presidential candidate John F. Kennedy asked Dr. Samuel Hayes, UM Professor of Economics, to draft a report on a potential peace corps. During a campaigning trip in Ann Arbor on October 14, 1960, Senator and presidential candidate John F. Kennedy challenged the students present to spend time giving international service, the idea that forms the basis of the Peace Corps.
The response from Michigan students was more than just favorable. Interested students formed a group called Americans Committed to World Responsibility (ACWR), in support of the idea of a peace corps. Around 250 students signed petitions agreeing to volunteer, and the ACWR traveled to Ohio, where they met Kennedy at the airport and delivered the petitions in person.
The positive response of Michigan students provided the needed momentum that turned the peace corps from an idea into a reality, and on March 1, 1961, the Peace Corps was officially created through an Executive Order. But Michigan's contributions weren't finished. Over 2000 Michigan alumni have served in the Peace Corps and contributed in other significant ways to the organization.
In 2010, the Peace Corps turned 50, and the University held a series of activities to celebrate this milestone and the University's role in the birth of the Corps. Among the events was a National Symposium focusing on the future of international service, ceremonies on the Michigan Union steps where Kennedy addressed the students in 1960, guest speakers, photo exhibits, and more.
The collection is divided into two series, Fiftieth Anniversary Videos and Archived Website.
The Peace Corps Office (University of Michigan) records contain information about the unit as well as the role of the University of Michigan in the development of the Peace Corps.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Peace Corps Office.; Voluntarism--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
University of Michigan. Peace Corps Office.; Voluntarism--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Peace Corps Office.; Voluntarism--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Digital moving image formats.; Web sites.
- Fiftieth Anniversary Videos
  Fiftieth Anniversary Videos, consists of videos of events held to commemorate the fiftieth anniversary of Senator Kennedy's speech at the Michigan Union. These videos were downloaded from YouTube.
  - First Ceremony on Michigan Union Steps, 2010
  - Second Ceremony on Michigan Union Steps, 2010
  - National Symposium: The Future of International Service
    - Welcome and Opening Remarks, 2010
    - First Panel Session -- Overview of the Current Landscape, 2010
    - Second Panel Session -- The Impact of International Service: What are the Lessons?, 2010
    - Third Panel Session -- New Initiatives and Policy Proposals, 2010
    - Fourth Panel Session -- Role of Universities, 2010
    - Closing Plenary and Keynote: "The Future of the Peace Corps", 2010
  - The Passing of the Torch Promotional Video, 2010
- Archived Website
  The Archived Website series documents the history of the creation of the Peace Corps and the fiftieth anniversary events. Content includes important news and announcements, stories of volunteers, and other facts and information relating to the creation and history of the Peace Corps at the University of Michigan. Starting in 2011, this archived website will be captured on a regular, ongoing basis as part of the University of Michigan Web Archives, hosted at http://webarchives.cdlib.org/a/universityofmichigan/.
  - 2011-2015
Related Materials
David Giltrow photograph collection finding aid is available online
Michiganensian photograph collection finding aid is available online
Out of the Blue: The Michigan Difference (television program) finding aid is available online
University of Michigan News and Information Services Photographs finding aid is available online
Kermit Krueger papers finding aid is available online
WUOM records (records of the Univeristy of Michigan radio station) finding aid is available online